A Guide to the Papers Pertaining to University of Virginia Alumni in World War I 1913-1920
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers Pertaining to University of Virginia Alumni in World War I 1913-1920
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
957-h
This collection consists of ca. 600 items (2 Hollinger boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library on October 1, 1940, possibly by Lewis Crenshaw.
Biographical/Historical Information
Much of the printed material and the photographs were gathered as part of the service of the University of Virginia European Bureau in Paris, France, directed by alumnus Lewis Crenshaw (1884-1947). Crenshaw left the University for Europe on December 1, 1917, and opened the office of the UVA Bureau on 8 Rue de Richelieu, Paris, to serve the approximately 3,000 alumni who served in World War I. At the office Crenshaw maintained photographs and war service records of University of Virginia alumni, forwarded mail and cables, stored personal effects for the men, handled alumni financial matters, purchased and shipped readily available articles to alumni, and took care of personal needs whenever possible. Crenshaw also compiled and published a UVA Overseas Alumni Directory, November 1, 1918.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 600 items (2 Hollinger boxes) 1913-1920, and includes printed material, photographs, and memorabilia, chiefly pertaining to the participation of the alumni of the University of Virginia in World War I, but also includes photographs of University of Virginia scenes and events.
Several of the memorabilia pertain to the career of one of the more famous of UVA alumni in World War I, James R. McConnell, of the Lafayette Escadrille. These include: a button from his uniform, a piece of shrapnel which wounded him, a strip of cloth from the fuselage of his airplane, a uniform cap worn by McConnell, a memorial plate in honor of McConnell from an American ambulance, and citations.
Printed material consists of pamphlets and advertisements concerning the American University Bureaus in Europe and the American University Union; miscellaneous business cards, name cards, postcards, campaign buttons, French advertisements and menus; newsclippings concerning UVA alumni and World War I; pamphlets, including "A History of the Operations and Activities of the 1st Battalion, 10th Field Artillery in the World War, 1914-1918," "Report of General John J. Pershing, U.S.A.," and an example of an American propaganda sheet; a University of Virginia alumni song book, Overseas Alumni Directory, Jefferson's Day Centennial Celebration, Paris, France, information sheets, and Certificate of Service, American Field Service in France, Ambulance Car No. 441; and Y.M.C.A., Red Cross, and miscellaneous tour guides, chiefly of France. Also present are two oversize French posters advertising "The Shackleton Expedition to the South Pole" at the Cinema Pathe, and the second showing of "The Bat" at the Theatre Femina.
Photographs are chiefly those of UVA alumni in uniform while serving in Europe during World War I, both identified and unidentified. A smaller group of photographs contains pictures of University of Virginia scenes and events prior to the entry of the United States into World War I. These include: the University of Virginia [Student Army Training Corp ?] in 1917, the Jefferson Day Celebration in 1919, Paris, France, Virginia football coaches and players, the Class of 1904, 1908, and 1914, Finals of 1913, the Corner ca. 1920, University fraternities and buildings, and Julius C. Gunter, Governor of Colorado.
For more information concerning UVA alumni and their participation in World War I please see the Papers of Lewis Crenshaw (# 2681) a closely related collection which includes war service records and many identified photographs.
Contents List
- Photographs--UVA Alumni in Europe, Identified ca. 1917-1918 (Box 1)
- Photographs--UVA Alumni in Europe, Unidentified ca. 1917-1918, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Photographs--University of Virginia Scenes and Events 1904-1920 (Box 1)
- Printed Material 1917-1918, n.d. (Box 2)
  re American University Bureaus in Europe and the American University Union
- Printed Material--Miscellaneous ca. 1917-1918 (Box 2)
- Printed Material--Newsclippings 1918-1920 (Box 2)
- Printed Material--Pamphlets 1919 (Box 2)
  re World War I
- Printed Material 1913-1919 (Box 2)
  re the University of Virginia
- Printed Material--Y.M.C.A., Red Cross, and Miscellaneous Tour Guides ca. 1914-1919 (Box 2)
- Memorablilia of James Rogers McConnell ca. 1914-1917
- Cap worn by James Rogers McConnell ca. 1914-1917 (Oversize Above 256)
- Citation of James Rogers McConnell 1918 (Oversize M-3)
- French Posters n.d. (Oversize 53)